You know the feeling you get
when you learn something new
about a health problem
you’ve been trying to reverse?
Maybe high blood pressure,
diabetes, or heart disease.
Well, there’s nothing I like better
than bringing you the information
that will help you do just that.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we explore
what dietary change
can simultaneously help detoxify mercury,
lead, and cadmium from the body.
We’ve previously explored
the issue of lead contamination in
calcium supplements like bone meal,
but it wasn’t just bone meal.
Substantial quantities of lead
were found in other, more common,
over-the-counter supplements.
Still, testing revealed continued
public health concern over bone meal,
but thankfully it’s not
as popular these days.
So, many of us are not likely
to get directly exposed to the lead
in bone meal any more –
but may get indirectly exposed
through the animals we eat.
In the U.S., five billion pounds
of meat and bone meal are produced
as slaughterhouse by-products every year.
What do we do with these millions
of tons every year?
We feed it back to farm animals,
particularly chickens.
Now, most of the lead in the bone meal
passes right through the animals
into their waste, but then we take
that waste (cow, pig, and chicken feces)
and feed it back to the animals again.
You guessed it!
So, you can see how the levels
of contaminants might
buildup in their body.
I’ve talked previously about
what that might mean for
making something like chicken soup,
but the original concern about
these kinds of feeding practices,
of feeding cows to cows,
and pigs and chickens,
was the spread of prion diseases,
like mad cow disease,
but it’s not just prions that
this kind of recycling can magnify;
but other toxic substances including lead.
So, a more plant-based diet
may be able to lower lead exposure,
and an even more plant-based diet
could theoretically lower
exposure even more,
but you’ve got to put it to the test.
But, should we expect to find a benefit?
Yes, lead is one of the
toxins found in meat,
but half of our dietary exposure
probably comes from plant foods.
Dietary modeling studies in Europe
suggest that vegetarians would be
exposed to about the same amount
of lead compared to
the general population,
with the exception of those
who eat a lot of wild game,
which can end up with a thousand times
more lead than most other foods.
In fact, a vegetarian diet
may even be higher in lead.
But, it’s not what you eat;
it’s what you absorb.
As we learned from the cadmium story,
the uptake of toxic heavy metals
from animal food sources into the human
intestinal lining cells may be higher
than that from vegetable sources.
That’s how you have a vegetarian
with some of the lowest concentrations
of lead and cadmium in her blood,
despite higher concentrations in her diet.
But you don’t know, until you…
put it to the test.
There seemed to be a tendency towards
higher fecal elimination of lead
following a change to a vegetarian diet,
with nine subjects on average tripling
their elimination of lead,
three unaffected, and four
dropping by about half.
But, the study only lasted a few months;
the difference wasn’t
statistically significant.
So, let’s try a year.
A shift towards a diet characterized
by large amounts of raw vegetables,
fruits, and unrefined foods, whole grains,
with the exclusion of
meat, poultry, fish, and eggs
(though it did include fermented dairy,
like a type of soured milk),
as well as cutting back on
processed foods and junk.
They took clippings of hair
before and after the shift,
and got significant reductions
in heavy metals,
including cutting their lead level
nearly in half.
And within three months,
their toxic heavy metals
went down, and stayed down.
How do we know it wasn’t
just a coincidence?
Because they went back up
a few years later
after the study was over,
after they went back to
more of their regular diet,
and their mercury, cadmium,
and lead levels shot back up
to where they were before.
Same thing with a different
group after two years.
The drop in mercury is easy to explain,
presumably due to the drastic drop
in fish consumption, and the drop
in alcoholic beverages may have
contributed to the drop in lead,
but it also could have been
a cadmium-like effect,
where the decrease in hair lead content
could be due to the dietary shift
resulting in less absorption of lead
into the body in the first place.
In our next story,
we look at one of the most concentrated
sources of the toxic metal cadmium.
Cadmium is known as a highly toxic metal
that represents a major hazard to human health.
It sticks around in our body for decades because
our body has no efficient way to get rid of it,
and may contribute to a variety of illnesses,
including heart disease, cancer, and diabetes.
Most recently, data suggests cadmium exposure
may impair cognitive performance even
at levels once thought to be safe.
Recent studies suggest
cadmium exposure may produce
adverse health effects at lower exposure levels
than previously predicted, including
increased risk of hormonal cancers.
For example, researchers on Long Island
estimated that about 40% of breast cancer
in the U.S. might be associated
with elevated cadmium levels.
Inhalation of cigarette smoke is one of the
major routes for human exposure to cadmium.
Seafood consumption is another dominant
route of human exposure in this study,
even more so than from cigarette smoke.
The highest levels, though, are found in organ
meats, but how many horse kidneys can you eat?
Because people eat so few
organs, grains and vegetables
actually end up contributing the largest amount.
But wait a second, whole grains and vegetables
are among the major dietary sources
of fiber, phytoestrogens, antioxidants
that may protect against breast cancer.
And indeed, even though the risk of breast cancer
goes up as women consume more and more cadmium,
even though on paper, most cadmium
comes from grains and vegetables,
breast cancer risk goes down the more and
more whole grains and vegetables women eat,
so maybe the animal sourced
cadmium is somehow worse,
or the benefits of plant foods just overwhelm
any adverse effects of the cadmium?
This study may have helped solve the mystery.
It’s not what we eat. It’s what we absorb.
Cadmium bioavailability from animal-based foods
may be higher than from vegetable-based foods.
There appears to be something in plants
that inhibits cadmium absorption.
In fact, if you add kale
to your boiled pig kidneys,
you can cut down on the toxic exposure.
Just one tablespoon of pig kidney and
we may exceed the daily safety limit—
unless we eat kale, in which case
we could eat a whole quarter cup.
The pronounced effects of the inhibitory factors
in kale point out the
importance of vegetable foods
in terms of prevention of
health hazards from cadmium
ingested as mixed diets in a real situation.
Even if a vegetarian diet contains more
lead and cadmium than a mixed diet,
it is not certain that it will give
rise to higher uptake of the metals,
because the absorption of lead and cadmium
is inhibited by plant compounds
such as fiber and phytate.
And it’s not just in lab animals.
Having whole grains in our
stomach up to three hours
before we swallow lead can
eliminate 90% of absorption,
thought to be due to phytates in whole
grains, beans and nuts grabbing onto it.
So vegetarians may have lower levels
even though they have higher intakes.
In fact, a significant decrease in the hair
concentrations of lead and cadmium was seen
after the change from an omnivorous
to a vegetarian diet,
indicating a lower absorption of the metals.
Here’s that study. They took folks
eating a standard Swedish diet
and put them on a vegetarian diet.
Lots of whole unrefined plant foods,
no meat, poultry, fish, eggs,
and junk food was discouraged.
00:03:58,9 --> 00:04:01,166
Here’s where they started out: a measure
of their mercury levels, cadmium levels,
and lead levels in their bodies.
Within three months on a vegetarian diet,
their levels significantly dropped,
and stayed down for the rest
of the year-long experiment.
But then they came back three years later,
three years after they stopped eating
vegetarian. And what did they find?
Their levels of mercury, cadmium
and lead shot back up.
Since the cadmium in plants is
based on the cadmium in soil,
plant-eaters that live in a really
polluted area like Slovakia —
which has some of the highest levels,
the so-called black triangle of pollution,
thanks to the chemical and smelting industries —
those who eat lots of plants
there can indeed build up
higher cadmium levels, especially
if you eat lots of plants.
It’s interesting, in spite of the significantly
higher blood cadmium concentration
as a consequence of a greater
cadmium intake from polluted plants,
all the antioxidants in those same plants were
found to help inhibit the harmful effects
of higher free radical production
caused by the cadmium exposure.
Still, though, in highly polluted areas
it might be an especially good idea
not to smoke, or eat too much
seafood or organ meats,
but even if we live in the Slovak Republic’s
black triangle of pollution,
the benefits of whole plant
foods would outweigh the risks.
In highly polluted areas, zinc supplements
may decrease cadmium absorption,
but I’d recommend against
multi-mineral supplements,
as they have been found to be
contaminated with cadmium itself.
Finally today,
did you know that the toxic heavy metal
contamination of Ayurvedic dietary supplements is,
in most cases,
intentional?
How do toxic heavy metals get into
Ayurvedic medicines in the first place?
In most cases, high levels of metals in
Ayurvedic traditional herbal preparations
result from intentional incorporation
of certain metallic preparations
like lead oxide, mercury sulfide,
arsenic trioxide.
Not to worry, though.
The heavy metals are claimed
to be detoxified by, for example,
heating and cooling the
herbal mixtures in cow’s urine.
This is not just an India issue.
Traditional medicines from around
the world incorporate these poisons.
In the Middle East, saoott is used
as a teething powder for infants.
It’s 51% lead;
one of a number of black lead-containing
substances used as teething powder.
Bokhoor is a Middle Eastern
practice of burning lead sulfides
to produce pleasant
fumes to calm infants.
They’ll be calm, all right.
Traditional Latin American medicines
include azarcon and greta—
almost pure lead,
used to treat constipation.
In traditional Chinese herbal medicine,
mercury is considered to have a
tranquilizing and (if you can believe it)
detoxifying effect.
But wait a second.
Haven’t these remedies
been used for centuries?
Sure, but that doesn’t
mean they’re safe.
In the West, let’s not forget
that bloodletting was among
the most common medical
practices performed by doctors
for almost 2,000 years.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Stay tuned for December 5, 2023
for the launch of my new one,
How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.